Guide to the Abraham Emmanuel Sautter Papers, 1800-1830
Department of Special Collections
Abraham Emmanuel Sautter Papers,
1800-1830
Special Collections M0534
Sautter, Abraham Emmanuel, fl. ca. 1820.
3 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1989.
Biographical Note
Abraham Emmanuel Sautter, fl. ca. 1820, along with his two brothers Donat and Daniel, appears to have owned a shipping brokerage firm through which they contracted to buy goods and have them shipped literally all over the world. They also contracted through other shipping companies and/or brokerage firms to obtain goods for themselves and for resale to their clients. Little can be determined about any of the Sautter brothers with regard to their personal lives. One could assume, however, that they were involved and well connected in French, Swiss and English commercial communities as they belonged to several international commercial societies. A.E. Sautter kept assiduous businesss records including copies of business correspondence, and duplicate accounts for himself and for his clients.
Scope and Content
The collection, spanning the years from 1800-1830, has been divided into four parts: outgoing and incoming correspondence to and from Abraham Emmanuel Sautter; accounts and invoices related directly to AE Sautter and Sautter Freres; correspondence and accounts to or from the Sautter's business associates with or without reference to them; and, miscellaneous documents which have been set aside for their interesting features or topics.
The collection consists entirely of papers which Abraham Emmanuel Sautter kept filed for the company. He and his brothers wrote and kept the files in French, although there is a significant amount of material, especially accounts and other documents in English, Prussian (German) and Dutch. Goods were obtained from all over the world: cotton and rice from South Carolina, sugar from the West Indies, opium, silk and cinnamon from Bombay and Bengal, and potash from Canada. The Sautter brothers themselves travelled significantly throughout Europe and Asia (and maybe even the United States) as can be seen from some of the addresses on the correspondence refering to St. Petersbourg, Constantinople, Florence, Amsterdam, Buenos Aires, Livorno and London.
Access Terms
Commerce.; Science and Industry--France.; Shipping--France.; Opium trade.; Potash industry and trade.; Tariff--France.; 19th century--France.
Container List
- Correspondence related to Abraham Emmanuel Sautter and Sautter Freres
  - Copies des Lettres
    - Ledger of personal letters, Copie des lettres, dated June 22, 1815-Oct. 25, 1815and Constantinople to Livourne. French. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ledger of copies of personal letters, Copies des lettres dated Oct. 27, 1815-Feb. 19, 1816.French. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ledger of copies of personal letters, Copies des lettres dated June 28, 1818-Aug. 19, 1820.French. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ledger of copies of personal letters, Copies des lettres dated Nov. 8, 1824-July 20, 1825.French. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Copies of personal letters, Copies des Lettres. 1813-1819.French. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Mr. Sautter from M. Pastuer et Fils, Co. 1815.Italian and French. All appear to be from Livorno. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Donat Sautter to AE Sautter. 1815.French. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence to AE Sautter. 1810-1819.French. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Various correspondence to AE Sautter. 1811-1820.French and English. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lettres de M.J. Barin pere du 10 avril 1822relatives a la liquidation des notres...Letter to AE Sautter-Sautter Freres. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Various correspondence to AE Sautter. 1809-1815.French. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Various correspondence to AE Sautter, 1809-1820.including filed letters from Lee & Fils, 1810-1812.French. Many are copies. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence from Sautter and some copies of letters. 1813-1819.French. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to AE Sautter from various. 1811-1818.Mostly French. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters, unknown addressee. 1808-1811. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AE Sautter and Sautter Freres accounts
    - Various invoices and delivery notices. 1809-1813.English, German, French. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Shipping orders, receipts, restaurant checks to, from and by AE Sautter. 1805-1810.Various languages. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Shipping orders and receipts to and from AE Sautter and Sautter Freres. 1809-1812.French and English. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Invoices to Sautter from RW&E Lee. 1810.Were held together with initialled paper sleeve. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Sautter accounts. 1808-1812.Various languages. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Sautter accounts. 1809-1813.Various languages. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Sautter accounts. 1809-1813.Various languages. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sautter accounts. 1807-1815.Various languages. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Sautter accounts. 1806-1812.Various languages. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Sautter accounts. 1803-1812.Various languages. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Sautter accounts. 1810-1813.Various languages. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Balance of accounts, 1806.By Sautter regarding all of his business associates and accounts. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sautter accounts and shipping orders. 1805-1810.Various languages. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Shipping bills for purchases for the accounts of A. Currie, 1810and Bernoully, 1810. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      (See additional Sautter accounts in oversize box. For a listing see oversize box contents at end of guide.)
- Other accounts and correspondence listed alphabetically by name:
  - Bellamy
    - Two copies of accounts labelled Bellamy. 1809.French. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bidermann
    - Handwritten letter from Bidermann. 1806.French. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      (See additional Bidermann material in oversize box)
  - Bornstein, Emmanuel
    - Incoming Correspondence. 1810-1811.Mostly French. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Incoming Correspondence. 1810-1812.French. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Incoming Correspondence. 1809-1816.French. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Accounts owed to E. Bornstein, Dec. 31, 1809. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Bornstein correspondence and accounts. 1810-1813.French. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bornstein, Sildare or Sildare
    - Incoming Correspondence to Sildare Bornstein. Various, including some from Donat Sautter. 1809.French. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Cazenove, James
    - Incoming Correspondence. 1812.French. (Box 3, Folder 15)
      (See more Cazenove correspondence and accounts in Oversize Box)
  - Duval, David
    - Correspondence and accounts from David Duval to AE Sautter. 1806-1810.French. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ellermann, A.
    (See correspondence and accounts in oversize box)
  - Mallett, Francis
    - Correspondence and accounts. 1805-1808.French and English. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Martinet, Jacques
    - Correspondence and documents. 1808-1809.French. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence and accounts. 1808-1809.French and English. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      (See additional Martinet accounts in oversize box)
  - Mommier, -
    - Correspondence from AE Sautter. 1820.French. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rettuar, -
    - Incoming Correspondence. 1807-1808,French. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      (See additional accounts and coorespondence in oversize box)
  - Sautter Freres, Daniel and Donat
    - Inventory of the Ship the Anna Maria with correspondence to Daniel Sautter. Printed contract with signatures by both Daniel and Donat Sautter. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to and from Donat Sautter. 1812-1817.French. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Unidentified or assorted miscellaneous
  - Various correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Various correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Shipping records, accounts and miscellany of interest
  - Various accounts, receipts and invoices from several different brokerage firms. 1810.French and English. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Various miscellaneous accounts and shipping records. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Various receipts for ships' passage. Ships mentioned include Heliogoland, Ruby and Betsey. n.d.English. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Various Form of Oath or affirmation.... c.1810,by Captain Frantz Gilbert of the Ship Jason. Appraisal of Ship Jason. Aug. 31, 1812. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Account Ledgers, Sautter et al
  - French. Aug. 3, 1803-June 22, 1824. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - German (Swiss). n.d.Very interesting seal. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - April 24, n.y. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Small account ledger, French. Contains accounts, engagements, appointments, lists. n.d.,although some reference to 1792 on first page. Various hands. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sautter opium trade accounts, 1810,through Brown, Rogers & Brown (a brokerage firm) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    (See oversize box for more account references to Opium Trade)
  - Various accounts. French and English. State of the Market in English. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lettres et papiers divers relatif aux comptes de Sieck & Hoeftmann regles definitivement avec T. Bernvalle le 27 fevrier 1813. 1810-1813.German, French and English. Sautter is mentioned in some. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - List of ships arrived. Probably belongs to Sautter. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ship contents. Dutch, Oct. 1804.Wax seal is completely intact. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Various accounts and receipts. c. 1806.German, French and English. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Shipping receipts. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    (See oversize box for more miscellaneous accounts in German)
  - Insurance policy for 100 pounds for the Ship Betsey. English, 10 March 1812.Printed announcements of sales and prices. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Decret Imperial which gives a list of import duties on certain materials. n.d.French. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Compilation of legislation relating perhaps to laws of trade from Geneva. c. 1820-1821.French. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    (For related documents see oversize box)
  - Ship Antonietta. Document signed by Dirk Mouller, ship's captain and three witnesses. Signed and sealed. Dutch, 1813. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    (See oversize box for a list of goods transported in the Antonietta)
  - Public Instrument of Protest and Declaration, English, March 2, 1812.Ship Ivan. Regarding damages done to a/some ships in Thompson's Ways. Signed by Thomas Molloy and Edward Evans. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    (See oversize box for additional miscellaneous documents)
- Oversize Materials
  - AE Sautter and Sautter Freres accounts. (Folder 1-3)
  - Additional accounts related to Mr. Bidermann. (Folder 4)
  - Correspondence to James Cazenove, July 10, 1807.French. (Folder 5)
  - Goods purchased through or for Mr. Ellermann, 1809.English and French. (Folder 6)
  - Accounts of Jacques Martinet, 1809-1809.French. (Folder 7)
  - Accounts and correspondence of Mr. Rettuar, Oct.-Nov. 1807.French. (Folder 8)
  - More accounts with reference to opium trade. (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous accounts in German. (Folder 10)
  - Additional compilation of legislation re: trade laws, c. 1820.French. (Folder 11)
  - List of goods transported in the Ship Antonietta. n.d.Dutch and English. (Folder 12)
  - Charter Party official document, Mar. 23, 1813.English. (Folder 13)
  - Accounts between Rigaud Battye and Sautter Freres, n.d.French. (Folder 14)
  - Balance des comptes, 1809.French. (Folder 15)